A Guide to the Papers of Florence Dickinson Stearns 1920-1955
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Florence Dickinson Stearns, 1920-1955
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
7494
This collection consists of 3,500 items (4 Hollinger boxes, 1.5 linear feet).
Sharon Defibaugh and Nina Aslan
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the University of Virginia Library by Mrs. J. Stuart Reynolds, Richmond, Virginia, on April 30, 1964.
Biographical/Historical Information
Stearns was a graduate of Columbia University and lived in Fredericksburg, Virginia, prior to the death of her husband, Franklin Stearns. Later she became associated with a metropolitan newspaper and became advertising manager of corporation in New York City. After she returned to Virginia, she again turned to newspaper work, writing sketches of Virginia poets (see news clippings 1934-1935, etc.) for The Richmond News Leader, articles on poetry, book reviews, and a series of articles entitled "Three Cornered Rendezvous," attempting to popularize the classic tradition in poetry. She also taught poetry technique at the Richmond Extension of the College of William and Mary. Stearns was a former president of the Poetry Society of Virginia, and member of the Catholic Poetry Society of America and Poetry Society of America. She first began seriously writing poetry in 1930, with her poetry appearing in various poetry magazines and anthologies, and a selection was published in book form in Strange Dimension in 1938.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of the papers of Virginia poet, Florence Dickinson Stearns (1883- ?), of Richmond, Virginia, ca. 3,500 items (4 Hollinger boxes, 1.5 linear feet), ca. 1920-1955, including manuscripts of her poetry, essays, articles, plays, speeches & lectures, reviews, and radio serials; a collection of poems used in her book, Strange Dimension(1938) published by G.P. Putnam's Sons, New York; correspondence; photographs; news clippings; printed and miscellaneous material.
Topics in the correspondence (Box 1) include: Stearns receiving The Richmond Academy of Arts Award (Andrews, 1932 Jun 22); composing music for three poems of Stearns to be used in a ballad and mention of Jean & John Powell (Annabel 1932 Oct 1); mention of his poem The Anniversary Ode and his book on psychics (Anspacher 1946 Feb 1, May 3, Oct 3); accepts position as a member of the Advisory Board of the Poetry Society of Virginia (Cabell 1934 Jun 29); the election of Stearns as a Regional Vice-President of the Poetry Society of America (Davidson 1951 Jul 16, Oct 3); discussion of the poetry of Stearns and a vicious review of Archibald MacLeish (Dillon 1953 Oct 3); high opinion and detailed discussion of Robert Frost (Dillon 1952 Feb 8); long discussion of John Nerber and mention of Dwight D. Eisenhower and the election (Dillon 1952 Feb 8); admiration for the poetry of Stearns (Freeman 1946 Jan 22); declines position as a member of the Advisory Board of the Poetry Society of Virginia but admires Stearns poetry (Glasgow 1934 Jun 18); inclusion of Stearns in an anthology of Virginia poets, Lyric Virginia To-day(Leitch 1931 Sep 22, Oct 1; 1932 Mar 10; May 18); criticism of Stearn's poetry (Leitch 1932 May 18); two poems by Mary Sinton Leitch (Leitch 1932 Nov 4); mention of Carl Sandburg and his goats (Leitch 1946 Sep 21); discussion of death and eternity (1952 Mar 9); mention of William Carlos Williams and W.H. Auden (Leitch 1952 Dec 7); an opinion of John Ciardi (Leitch 1953 Nov 25 & 28); and mention of Marianne Moore (Meacham 1955 Jun 9).
Contents List
- Correspondents of Florence Dickinson Stearns
  - Mrs. Olive W. Andrews to Florence Dickinson Stearns 1932 Jun 22 (Box 1)
  - Annabel to Florence Dickinson Stearns 1932 Oct 1 (Box 1)
  - Louis K. Anspacher to Florence Dickinson Stearns 1946-1947 (Box 1)
  - Martha Bianchi to Florence Dickinson Stearns n.d. (Box 1)
  - James Branch Cabell to Florence Dickinson Stearns 1934 Jun 29 (Box 1)
  - Gustav Davison to Florence Dickinson Stearns 1951 (Box 1)
  - George Dillion to Florence Dickinson Stearns 1927-1953 (Box 1)
  - Huntly Drummond to Florence Dickinson Stearns 1952 (Box 1)
  - Douglas S. Freeman to Florence Dickinson Stearns 1945-1946 (Box 1)
  - Ellen Glasgow to Florence Dickinson Stearns 1934 Jun 18 (Box 1)
  - Leigh Hanes to Florence Dickinson Stearns n.d. (Box 1)
  - Robert Hunt to Florence Dickinson Stearns 1933 Apr 4 (Box 1)
  - Mary Sinton Leitch to Florence Dickinson Stearns 1931-1953 (Box 1)
  - Harry Meacham to Florence Dickinson Stearns 1955 Jun 9 (Box 1)
  - Corinne Melchers to Florence Dickinson Stearns 1930-1933 (Box 1)
  - Miss Phalin to Florence Dickinson Stearns n.d. (Box 1)
  - Louise Powell to Florence Dickinson Stearns 1936 Oct 21 (Box 1)
  - Wayne Miller to Florence Dickinson Stearns 1930 (Box 1)
  - Florence Dickinson Stearns to Mr. Vinal 1930 Sept (Box 1)
  - Florence Dickinson Stearns to Unknown 1938 Jul 20 (Box 1)
  - Alexander Wilbourne Weddell to Florence Dickinson Stearns 1939-1940 (Box 1)
  - Excerpts from letters to Florence Dickinson Stearns n.d. (Box 1)
- Manuscripts & Other Papers
  - Certificate of Membership In The Society Of The South 1939 Aug 11 (Box 1)
  - "The Dark Closet" n.d. (Box 1)
    A serial for radio by Florence Dickinson Stearns
  - Essays by Florence Dickinson Stearns (A-G) 1932, 1935, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Essays by Florence Dickinson Stearns (H-Z) 1932, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Lessons on writing poetry by Florence Dickinson Stearns n.d. (Box 1)
  - Manuscripts by Florence Dickinson Stearns n.d. (Box 2)
    Unidentified
  - News clippings 1932-1934 (Box 2)
  - News clippings 1935 (Box 2)
  - News clippings 1936-1952 (Box 2)
  - News clippings n.d. (Box 2)
  - Notebook belonging to Stearns with some Autobiographical Articles n.s. (Box 2)
  - Photographs of Florence Dickinson Stearns n.d. (Box 2)
  - Plays by Florence Dickinson Stearns n.d. (Box 2)
  - Poems (A) 1944, n.d. (Box 2)
    Including, Abyss, Admonition, Adopted from Epictetus, Advice to Them Who Give Too Much, Affirmation, Afternoon In A Garden, All Of Life's Splendor, " All's Done, All's Said," Alone, Ambassador, An American Blinded In The Spanish War, And So We Thank Thee, Anniversary, Answer In Green, Apparition, The Apple Tree, An Appreciation, Argument For Travel, The Artist, As I Went Down A Woodland Way, As Your Friends, Atavism, The Author
  - Poems (B) n.d. (Box 2)
    Including, Banishment, Barbed Wire, Bargain, " Because The Tide Of Progress..," The Bend In The Road, Bertram Sale, Better Oblivion, Bond, Bond Or Free?, Brave Adventure, Bright Avowal, Bright Borderland, Bright Destiny, Bright Futile Hours, Bronchitis..An Impossible, But Never Love.
  - Poems (C) 1937, n.d. (Box 2)
    Including, Can The Heart Retain, Caprice, Captive(3 versions), Carillon, Celebration, A Certain Lane, A Certain Orchid, Change Of Heart, Chart, Cherry Tree, " The Choice Is There..," Christmas, Christmas Day, Circles, City Street, Clear Word, Compensation(2 versions), Confidence, Conquest, Conspirators, " Could We But Find..," Courage, " Courage" and " When She Is Gone," Creation On Paper, Cross Purpose.
  - Poems (D) 1921, n.d. (Box 2)
    Including, " Daring Alone..," Dark Bridge, Dark Flower, Dark Guest, Dark Hope, The Day That My Road Ends, " Death Makes So Curt A Call..," The Deer, Desert The Flame, Destiny, Destiny( A Thanksgiving Poem), " Do You Still Hold..," Document In Evidence, Don Juan On The Cliffs, The Dream, Dual Flame, Dubious Hour, Dust And This Smoke Called Life, " Dust" and " Windows".
  - Poems (E-F) 1944, n.d. (Box 2)
    Including, Eagle, Easter Bells, Eclipse, Elizabeth's Garden, Elopement In Blue, Enemies Of Peace, " An Erudite Poet..," The Escapist, Etching, Faith, " Father, We Come In Praise..," Fear, Fingers Of Bronze, " Five Casual Swans Were Going..," For Elizabeth, For Poets Of The Left Wing, For Two, Four Winds, Freedom In Captivity, A Friend I've Never Seen, Fugitive, Futility.
  - Poems (G-H) n.d. (Box 3)
    Including, " A Generous Old Fellow..," " Get The Light..," Goal, The Gossip, Gratitude, The Great Gift, Grim Architect, Guest, Hang The Wreath, " Have No Commerce With The Ocean..," " He That Is Without Sin Among You..," Her Diary, Her Room, Here In This Wood, The Hermit, High Estate, Hold To The Dream, The House, House On The Hill, How Are You Faring, How Much To Hoard, " How Soon Are Those Forgotten..," How The Dark Lifted, H2SO4, Hydrangeas, Hymn.
  - Poems (I) 1930, n.d. (Box 3)
    Including, " I Am Not All Alone..," I Cannot See The World For You, I Fear The Twilight, I Flee Forever, If In The Language Of The Polished Leaves, " I Know That He Is Waiting..," I Must Be Going, I Shall Never Forget, I Shall Not Go To Seek The Town, " I Shall Stand Quiet By This Old Wall," I Want To Talk About Myself, " Iconoclast Of All The Things We Hate..," If You Could Be The Moon Tonight, If Youth Had Been Adept To Prove, Illusion, Imminence, Impermanence, In A Garden, In An Old Garden, " In Bethlehem's Streets..," In Praise Of Green, In Your Name, Independence, Indian Summer, Indifference, The Indifferent Years, Infantile Paralysis, Inheritance, Injunction, Inscrutable, Interegnum, The Islands, Island Summer.
  - Poems (J-L) n.d. (Box 3)
    Including, Journey(2 versions), Journey By Water, Journey Through Space, July The Forth, Knowledge, " The Lake Curved Here..," The Last Voyage, " The Leaves No Longer..," " Let Him That Is Without Sin..," Let Him Who Will, Let The Half Gods Go, Let Us Rejoice, Letter In Response, Letter To Hymenaeus, " The Light Persistence..," Limericks About Creatures: The Owl, Beavers, The Little Less Than Real, The Little Plant, Looking Backward, Lost Bird, Love And Art, Lullaby.
  - Poems (M-N) n.d. (Box 3)
    Including, Magic Carpet For Boredom, Maginot, Magnolias, " A Man Who Was Nurtured..," March Wind, Mask, " Men Meet, Talk Wisely..," The Message To Frances, Miracle, Mirrors, " Miss Gresham, Mr. Cabell..," Moment In Flight, The Moon Rides Inward Still, Moon Song, Moon Rise, Morning Glories, Mourners, My Brother Eats His Breakfast, My Eyes Accustomed Grew, My Hour, Mystic, Need, Negro Lullaby, No Eye Can Tell, " No Flower Owed Allegiance..," No Loss, No Text For Faltering, " No Word Could Compass..," A Noon That Is Here, Not Built By Hands.
  - Poems (O-P) n.d. (Box 3)
    Including, O Come Not Near To Love, O Valiant Root, " O Vanished With All Youth's Wide Wonder..," The Oak, Obsequies, The Occasion Is Indeed Complete, Offering, Old Diary, Old Query, Old Sampler, The Old Westmoreland Club, On Daydreaming, On Meeting An Elusive Personality, One Other Autumn, Our Men Down Under, " Our Years May Lean..," " Over My Shoulder..," Over The Back Fence, Ownership, Pagan, Park Bench, Passion, Pawn Of Time, " Peace On Earth Is Legended..," Pegasus, Pentecost, Pentecostal Hymn, Perchance To Dream, A Poet's Garden, Plain Women, Planned Economy, " Pondering On Life's Equation..," " The Pool Was Just As We Left It..," The Pool-Evening, The Pool-Morning, Portal, Portrait(2 versions), A Portrait, Printed Notice, Problem In Subtraction, Promise, Protest.
  - Poems (Q-R) 1950, n.d. (Box 3)
    Including, Quest, " The Rain Of An Unearthly Light..," The Reader And The Left- Wing Poet, The Reason "Why," Recognition, " The Red And Gold Impermanence..," Rejected, Rendezvous, Rendezvous In Space Resignation, The Return, A Revolt Against Poets Called Ultra-Modern, Richmond, Richmond (A Sonnet To Beauty), Riverside Drive, Rivalry, The Road, Robert Browning, Robert Hillyer At Williamsburg, Romance, Romance At The Bridge Table.
  - Poems (S) 1939, n.d. (Box 3)
    Including, Sabbath, Samain (Irish Halloween), Sara Teasdale Book On A Counter, Sea Scape, Security With These, Self-Revelation, The Shadow, Shelter, Short Precarious Hour, Signature, " Since You Have Gone The Place Is Crowded With You..," So To A Man Dismayed, So Valueless To Me, Soft Was The Word, Song(3 versions), The Song, Song Of Caledon, Sonnet, Soul Mate, A Soul That Is I, Southern Right, Space, Spirit, Spring Avowal, The Square Terrific, Stepping Stone, Storm, Storm Clouds.
  - Poem (S-T) n.d. (Box 4)
    Including, Strange Town, Stratagem, Strength, Strength For The Valley, Superior Breath, Swift Passage, Symbol, Symbol In Reply, Table Setting, Taking Notes, Teak, Terms Of Tomorrow, " The Terrace Still Welcomes The Sun. .," Thanksgiving, " There Are Times..," " There Is A Path From Yesterday..," " There Is A Word Of Plural Number..," " There Is No Earth..".
  - Poems (T-continued) 1937, n.d. (Box 4)
    Including, There Would Be Light, Three Bright Christmas Wishes, They Live Again, " This Land Fringed Almost To The..," This Other Country, This Question Of Ignorance, " This Shallow Pool..," " This Was No Day..," " Thou Hast Made Known..," Thrall, Three Worlds, Threnaday, The Tie That Separates, The Time Is Now, Tip Top Graham, To A Certain Poet, To An Impatient Seeker After Fame, To A Restless Artist, To Edwin Quarles (A Tribute), To Ellen, To Her, To Lisa Summer, To Poets At The Crossroads, To Those In A Machine Civilization, Tonight The Moon, Too Light To Bear, " Tonight The Moon Will..," Transitory, Treasure, " The Tree Drips Silver Light..," Twilight And Musk, Two Letters, Two Sonnets (The Pool), Two Worlds.
  - Poems (U-Z) 1922, 1939, n.d. (Box 4)
    Including, Uncut Volumes, Unidentified Poem, A Valentine, Valueless To Me and This Smoke Called Life, Values, Vanity, Victims Of Art, Victory, The Vision Of My Own Imagining, Waited Interview, Walter Johnson, War In The Pacific, The Watcher, We Knew The Secret Of This Sycamore, What Is There To Sing About, " What Through The Spirit..," When The Leaves Go Slack, Where Love Has Been, Where You Alone Can Go, " While Shepherds Were Waiting..," White Peacock In The Moon, Whose Heart Is Faun, Wild Ducks, The Will To Do, The Wind's Way Is In Your Way, The Yes-Sayer, " You Girdled In Spirit..." " Your High Estate..," Your Hour Will Come, " Your Linotype Has Brought..," Your Name, Your Voice, Zero Marker.
  - Poems by other Authors 1898-1851, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Poems selected for Strange Dimensionn.d. (Box 4)
  - Programs and Announcement 1936-1942 (Box 4)
  - Reviews by Florence Dickinson Stearns n.d. (Box 4)
  - Reviews of Strange Dimension by Florence Dickinson Stearns 1938, 1939, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Speeches and Lectures by Florence Dickinson Stearns n.d. (Box 4)